<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:/collections/6bf4bc983ce72870e7c022c496be3b57</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/collections/6bf4bc983ce72870e7c022c496be3b57.atom"/>
  <title>Journal of Brief Ideas: Collection Mydeas</title>
  <updated>2024-06-24T16:55:03Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1030</id>
    <published>2022-12-03T19:49:04Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-15T22:10:33Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/7ea1e6e01122741e26a887b18178db3b"/>
    <title>Peer-review reforms necessary for transfiguring the literature curation sector</title>
    <doi/>
    <content type="html">Peer-review is considered an impeccable method for the knowledge creation pipeline through scholarly publishing. However, there is no definite universal guideline for conducting and validating the peer-review process; neither do peer reviewers receive credits for the amount of time and intellect they invest in this. 

In this chaotic situation, I like to recommend the following:
1) Development and periodic revision of an international guideline which is flexible to adopt by journals of all disciplines.
2) Recognition of peer-reviewers precious time and remarks. It should be mandatory to include the names of peer-reviewers at the end or somewhere in the published manuscript. 
3) Competitive value of peer-review needs to be credited during the recruitment and promotion of researchers. It must be emphasized in the job description in order to outmode the conventional mindset.  

All stakeholders involved in this reform ranging from publishing houses to recruiting managers must cooperate. An international peer-review council has to be established to develop, execute and revise the standard guidelines. Regular training can be arranged to propagate peer-reviewing skills and awareness of the importance of it.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Dutta, Debprasad</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
