<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:/collections/f3859563fb629e97ffca1fbc532daa6c</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/collections/f3859563fb629e97ffca1fbc532daa6c.atom"/>
  <title>Journal of Brief Ideas: Collection Astro Ideas</title>
  <updated>2016-08-16T18:05:13Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/327</id>
    <published>2016-08-04T03:36:28Z</published>
    <updated>2016-08-15T21:57:38Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/59bde655f99d29f685702717316e06f3"/>
    <title>The NASA K2 Mission has yet to observe an analog of Tabby's Star</title>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.59494</doi>
    <content type="html">Tabby's Star is a main sequence F-class star ([KIC 8462852](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KIC_8462852)) observed by the NASA Kepler spacecraft to undergo significant aperiodic dimming activity across a four year baseline. The light curve was noted as novel amongst a pool of ~150,000 targets through visual inspection performed by participants of the [PlanetHunters.org](https://www.planethunters.org/) project. [Boyajian, et al. (2015)](http://arxiv.org/abs/1509.03622) reported an analysis which attempted to model the enigmatic behavior under various scenarios, with a swarm of exo-comets offered as a potential (but problematic) leading explanation. Subsequent follow-up studies failed to detect a significant IR excess or the presence of close stellar companions. [Wright, et al. (2015)](http://arxiv.org/abs/1510.04606) offered an alternative explanation invoking transits of alien-megastructures, which may not produce a detectable IR excess or radial velocity signal. 

To date, a robust model to explain the behavior of Tabby's Star remains elusive.

The Kepler spacecraft is now observing a series of new ecliptic fields ([K2](http://keplerscience.arc.nasa.gov/)) and has accumulated observations of ~165,000 additional targets. Continued visual inspection of these public data has failed to recover an analog to KIC 8462852. Lack of such a detection suggests that the aperiodic dimming indeed represents a rare astrophysical phenomenon, regardless of the true root cause mechanism involved. Future photometric surveys by K2 and TESS will offer additional opportunity to search for such analogs.

</content>
    <author>
      <name>LaCourse, Daryll</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
