<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:/ideas</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas.atom"/>
  <title>Journal of Brief Ideas: Ideas from the last week</title>
  <updated>2024-10-13T23:47:36Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1861</id>
    <published>2024-10-13T23:47:36Z</published>
    <updated>2024-10-17T06:00:22Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/86c69daa76f4467c19ec017327e411e4"/>
    <title>The Biological Rationality of Racial Fetishes</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13942990</doi>
    <content type="html">Sexual racism is a problematic feature of dating and pair-bounding preferences. It is seen as reinforcing racial stereotypes and dating hierarchies (Bedi, 2015) among majority ethnicities. Racial fetishization has subjected minority women to harassment (Buchanan et al. 2018), violence (Olive, 2012), and sexual objectification (Zhang et al. 2024).

Many researchers have written about the ethical issues of racial fetishes, but few have attempted to explain the cause within the context of biology. The Biological Rationality of Racial Fetishes seeks to expound a biological explanation for this phenomenon.  Racial fetishes could be viewed as an adaptive heuristic to avoid inbreeding. Inbreeding is associated with an increased incidence of genetic disorders (Alvarez et al. 2011).

This concept is a two-tiered sorting mechanism that relies on phenotypical differences and cultural stereotypes, the assumption being that if a potential mate has a different skin color, accent, bone structure, and or cultural background, there are no familial ties. These differences signal to the potential suitor that they will avoid the risk of inbreeding.

There is no excuse for the suboptimal societal outcomes of race-based sexual objectification, but this is merely an attempt to find a biologically rational explanation.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Clark, Peter</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1762</id>
    <published>2024-10-06T01:41:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-10-17T06:00:22Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/1608f44fd7661690f58539a3486eaf71"/>
    <title>Energy Transition from Natural Gas to Hydrogen: Insights on Hydrogen Production from Aluminum silicate in Clay-Rich Rocks</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13942987</doi>
    <content type="html">Hydrogen is recognized as a clean fuel that significantly contributes to reducing greenhouse gas emissions, making it essential for the energy transition. However, large-scale hydrogen storage is challenging due to its volatility, compressibility, and flammability (Aslanehad et al., 2023). One promising option is geological storage, which is widely available in Malaysia and offers significant capacity. Despite this, the chemical properties of clay minerals in sandstone reservoirs, especially in relation to hydrogen storage, are poorly understood (Au &amp; Leong, 2013; Jian et al., 2016). This lack of knowledge limits their use in energy storage and related applications. This study focuses on improving hydrogen production efficiency by examining the effects of brine (NaOH)-helium injection and analyzing petrophysical properties in sandstone core samples. The interaction between clay occlusions and brine-helium injection, potentially a game-changing storage method, has not been well-explored. Synthetic brine (NaOH) will be used to study the clay's reactivity in the pore medium in the presence of helium, with the goal of determining hydrogen output and evaluating the potential for small-scale geostorage. </content>
    <author>
      <name>abdul rahman, muhd nur ismail</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1630</id>
    <published>2024-09-14T14:10:20Z</published>
    <updated>2024-10-17T06:00:22Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/4724fe12f939175b4ac3c0ca6ed89a56"/>
    <title>Converting Snakemake workflows to Nextflow with nf-core modules using a fine-tuned LLM</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13942979</doi>
    <content type="html">A useful application of AI in bioinformatics is the automatic transformation of Snakemake workflows into Nextflow, leveraging nf-core modules and subworkflows where available. As bioinformatics pipelines become increasingly complex, the ability to seamlessly transition between workflow languages is essential, particularly in collaborative environments where diverse teams may prefer different tools. A fine-tuned LLaMA model or an OpenAI custom GPT  could be trained to interpret the structure and logic of a Snakemake workflow on GitHub and convert the workflow to Nextflow. This model could identify where existing nf-core modules and subworkflows can replace custom scripts, simplifying the process and ensuring adherence to best practices in pipeline design. Such a system would reduce the burden of manually translating workflows, enabling researchers to take advantage of Nextflow’s scalability and reproducibility without significant overhead.

To implement this, one could fine-tune an existing language model on a dataset of paired Snakemake and Nextflow workflows, with special emphasis on nf-core standards. The model would need to be able to understand both the structure of workflow definitions and the underlying bioinformatics tools being invoked. Additionally, the model should query nf-core’s module registry to determine where standard subworkflows can be integrated, further enhancing workflow consistency and reducing redundancy.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Turner, Stephen</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1498</id>
    <published>2024-08-07T17:00:07Z</published>
    <updated>2024-08-09T06:00:25Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/e809a8d55cf2685c3d15fea9d9d9aec3"/>
    <title>À la Carte Acceptance: A Critical Examination of Selective Inclusion in Modern DE&amp;I Practices</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13279131</doi>
    <content type="html">Recently Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion (DE&amp;I) initiatives have gained significant traction in corporate, educational, and social environments. These initiatives aim to foster environments where diverse individuals feel valued, included, and treated equitably. However, a deeper examination reveals a phenomenon that can be described as "à la carte acceptance." This term encapsulates the selective approach to inclusion, where only specific social groups benefit from DE&amp;I efforts, while others remain marginalized. This selective acceptance undermines the true essence of diversity and equity, raising critical questions about the sincerity and comprehensiveness of modern DE&amp;I practices.

The concept of à la carte acceptance suggests a pick-and-choose method in embracing diversity. Corporations and institutions often highlight their commitment to DE&amp;I by showcasing efforts to support certain groups, such as women, racial minorities, and the LGBTQ+ community. While the progress made in these areas is commendable, the focus on these groups can sometimes overshadow the exclusion of others. For instance, individuals with disabilities, older adults, neurodivergent individuals, and those from less visible ethnic minorities might find themselves overlooked in the broader DE&amp;I discourse. This selective focus creates an illusion of comprehensive inclusion while perpetuating inequalities for those who do not fit into the selectively chosen categories.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Hämäläinen, Mika K</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1465</id>
    <published>2024-08-03T10:11:07Z</published>
    <updated>2024-08-24T10:09:58Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/bb267eca386b7e59d9cc185511d66e02"/>
    <title>The Parenting Balance Matrix: Mapping Parental Influence on Child Development</title>
    <doi/>
    <content type="html">The Parenting Balance Matrix is a visual framework designed to illustrate how the combination of two parents' styles influences a child's development. It categorizes parenting approaches along a spectrum, from "Absent" to "Overbearing," for each parent, and highlights the intersections that form an optimal balance. Central to the model is the "Ideal parenting balance," indicating a balanced and mindful approach where both parents are encouraging, either liberating or cautious.

The gradient background indicates the increasing likelihood of greater external influences on the child as parental balance deviates from the ideal. The role of external influences is becoming increasingly prominent, given that today's children are introduced to smartphones and the internet at a very early age.

This matrix provides a clear, intuitive guide for parents to reflect on and adjust their parenting strategies, promoting a harmonious and supportive environment for their children. The model's strengths lie in its simplicity, accessibility, and visual appeal, making it a valuable tool for parents and educators alike. Although not intended to seek a perfect parenting style, which is perhaps an impossible task, it is hoped that the model would nonetheless spark further in-depth research into the dynamics of parenting in an ever-changing world.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Sabapathy, Karthik</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1432</id>
    <published>2024-07-29T16:10:23Z</published>
    <updated>2024-09-19T02:10:16Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/326de755c8bdb494b354e804fb09a74e"/>
    <title>The need and format for publications is stifling innovation and science adoption</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13129574</doi>
    <content type="html">Nowadays two problems affect science.
- The *quantum* necessary to publish scientific discovery is large. This not only heavily increases the time needed for publication, but it also impacts the time required to stay up to date with the scientific literature, stifling innovation. This is a problem generally accepted and recognized: in fact, the "Journal of Brief Ideas" was created with this exact goal in mind ([Harris, 2015](/ideas/17b997da912f99ce9988a47f42b52692)).
- Back when science was just starting out, scientists were used to publishing for the general public. In fact, most of the *classics* books on "science" can be read by everyone, although the general, lay reader may find some difficulties in this activity. This probably increases the chances that science is discovered, and adopted.

Would it be possible to evaluate the impact that the standards of publications have on science? If so, how? Should researchers be more "conscious" of the general public, allowing for broader access to science and potentially improving our overall culture? Should researchers be encouraged to disseminate their research to the general public? If so, how should these changes be proposed to academia?

_**Disclaimer:** I got this idea while reading: ["How to Read a Book" by Adler, M. &amp; Van Doren, C.](https://www.google.com/books/edition/How_to_Read_a_Book/Xg-CBAAAQBAJ?hl=it&amp;gbpv=0&amp;kptab=overview). Further research is needed to confirm the hypotheses._</content>
    <author>
      <name>Esposito, Andrea</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1399</id>
    <published>2024-07-24T10:18:55Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-30T06:00:36Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/cecf7e1646a5f412b2c60014d226ef87"/>
    <title>Capitalist capital allocation as meta-reward function for AI training model</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13129560</doi>
    <content type="html">Machine learning protocols utilize rewards function during training as a means of tuning parameters toward obtaining desirable outputs from a model. One challenge for the current AI industry is the difficulty of translating real-world utility into reward functions for individual models that are trained primarily on training sets of online content, which seldom has an accurate valuation of its real-world utility attached to it. However, computing resources are allocated to different models based on their value to the companies producing and, at a higher layer, capital in the form of investment or revenue is preferentially allocated to those companies whose models are perceived as having higher potential for real-world utility. In essence, this process functions as a meta-reward function for the AI ecosystem overall.  </content>
    <author>
      <name>Stacey, Neil Thomas</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1366</id>
    <published>2024-07-18T09:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-30T06:00:36Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/a4aa11e8ee7192307721e18785a5947e"/>
    <title>Can the Weddell Sea (Southern Ocean) be a sink for atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2)?</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13129552</doi>
    <content type="html">The source water mass of the Weddell Sea is Circumpolar Deep Water (CDW), which is high in CO2. Subsurface CDW is upwelled into the surface layer which tends to cause some CO2 outgassing. CDW is also involved in bottom water formation together with a surface water component, which generates water with CO2 content smaller than that of CDW. Both processes would tend to turn the Weddell Sea into a CO2 source to the atmosphere. 
A sink function can only exist if water that is enriched in CO2 in the Weddell Sea is transferred out of it. Surface water is exported but has less CO2 than CDW. Similar holds for exported deep water. Modified CDW of the central Weddell is CO2-enriched; remineralization of organic matter, sinking from the surface layer, causes this CO2-enrichment. This organic matter has been produced near the surface, causes CO2 under-saturation which leads to uptake of atmospheric CO2. Whether the Weddell Sea is a CO2 sink in the end depends on the export rate of organic matter from the surface layer in relation to the strength of CDW upwelling. The offshore Weddell Sea is pivotal, not the coastal regions as claimed for long times.
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Hoppema, Mario</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1333</id>
    <published>2024-07-10T09:40:13Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-30T06:00:36Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/63cbe19fe1e7eebc379231e1fb8430a1"/>
    <title>The Atlas of Human Range</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13129532</doi>
    <content type="html">The Atlas of Human Range (AoHR) is an [Atlas of Human Interests](/ideas/98e3f9cea2b150029d0205070f59db05) evolution. The AoHR, however, maps a vast spectrum of human inner and outer manifestations, spanning temperament, personality, interests, knowledge orientations, soft and hard skills, and important behaviors and outcomes (e.g., well-being, health, income). Thus, it seeks to cover lifespace from early traits to mature realization.

Central to the AoHR is the identification of unique individual configurations in comparison to the aggregate of many individuals. The AoHR “positions” an individual within a larger, multidimensional “map,” hence the term “atlas.” It can be an important scientific tool to help individuals understand their comparative advantages and identify the most fruitful areas for growth. With a multidimensional and integrative approach, the atlas can also aid in estimating varying levels of “resistance” (e.g., competition, perceived profile distance) in different career paths, considering a combination of the individual's multidimensional profile and aggregate data from a large number of individuals. This can help answer what is special about oneself and how to contributing meaningfully to society. 

It can also serve as a measure of [polymathy](/ideas/5ff33bee3321766b7bb581634aebfd72). Breadth is gauged by the diversity and disparatedness in one's knowledge profile. Depth relates to a minimum skill or [expertise](/ideas/ffab4037c166cc20b1aebfadb090f205) requirement in each domain. Integration is gauged through synergies between skillsets.
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Araki, Michael</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1300</id>
    <published>2024-07-04T15:18:31Z</published>
    <updated>2024-09-19T02:09:35Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/3287afafe63be234ea925429906c8b1b"/>
    <title>Tracking smartphone screen time during weight-loss trials: an indirect means of exploring semaglutide's efficacy against addiction</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12660262</doi>
    <content type="html">Screen time has been identified as not just a strong correlate with addiction, but as a predictor and even as an addiction in and of itself. Semaglutide, better known by the brand name Ozempic, is widely used as an anti-obesity drug and it, along with related compounds such as Liraglutide, are also under investigation as potential treatments for addiction. The same neurological reward mechanisms and neurochemical pathways involved in dysregulated eating play a role in numerous addictions, and early indications are that these medications may be effective at curbing cravings for addictive substances much as they curb food cravings. Screen-time, with its close link to addiction and its arguable status as a widespread addiction in itself, would be a simple marker to track during clinical trials of these medications for other purposes, easily and inexpensively added on to existing trial protocols to yield insight into Semaglutide's effects on addiction, procrastination and productivity.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Stacey, Neil Thomas</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
