<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:/collections/665ad2615912c50639f0d17204b9e16e</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/collections/665ad2615912c50639f0d17204b9e16e.atom"/>
  <title>Journal of Brief Ideas: Collection Mystery </title>
  <updated>2022-08-19T17:08:10Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/673</id>
    <published>2020-02-08T22:05:43Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-09T06:00:38Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/9a63eee85a038908a9e8cdd223344eb3"/>
    <title>Stonehenge: Solstice Opens Path to a Neolithic Afterlife</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3660066</doi>
    <content type="html">Stonehenge was a massive effort for a calendar when the climate supports year round crops. Cups and Rings stones found throughout the UK were more likely the working calendars. They marked the field indicating when/where/what crop to harvest, using astronomical references thought to be the primary purpose of Stonehenge.

Additional religious motivation supports calendar, cremation + place of healing theories. Absence of god imagery points to directly communing with deities.

Newgrange Kerbstone (Ireland, tomb, 300 yrs earlier) imagery similar to shape of Stonehenge and moon. Also:

Motifs resembling two constellations in eastern winter sky:
Triskele - Winter Triangle
3 consecutive spirals  - Orion's belt
Correlation between death/winter, in keeping with agrarian culture.

Newgrange exterior Kerbstone, left side, roughly translated: 
Here these seeds (the dead) moved from earthly fields, crossed the bridge (path) to new fields in the sky (triangles + moon/horseshoe arc) Right side: (represents afterlife activity)

Solstice perhaps when "path" opens, Orion's belt indicates route. Stonehenge built to represent moon. Bluestones should glow with cool light (moon fire) when heated.

Stonehenge should be lit when Orion rises in the east, fire around every bluestone, a signal for the ancestors to receive the newly dead about to cross over.
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Neumann, Erica</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
