<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:/collections/d8499e166d90c44daab4e37350443c70</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/collections/d8499e166d90c44daab4e37350443c70.atom"/>
  <title>Journal of Brief Ideas: Collection Human Evolution</title>
  <updated>2020-07-30T21:40:07Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/79</id>
    <published>2015-02-20T23:36:39Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-28T17:39:34Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/120b1f47e6890550933c0958d25e7f1c"/>
    <title>Endurance Hunting aa a Driver for Sexual Dimorphism and Role Differentiation</title>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15563</doi>
    <content type="html">Early humans were endurance hunters. They were successful in long distance pursuit of prey. This behavioral strategy is believed to be at least 2MM years old, predating h. sapiens, and persists in Kalahari bushmen and the Tarahumara, amongst others. However, long distance running reduces body fat to &lt;10%, which in females is inadequate for fertility. Thus endurance hunting may have been an early driver of role differentiation (male hunters vs. female gatherers) with female gathering allowing a maintained &gt;20% body fat composition, and maintained fertility.
Insofar as any female runners  would be at a fertility disadvantage it is possible that gatherer females, with dimorphically distinct evolutionary modern body habitus would have been regarded positively in comparison. 
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Katz, Richard</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/373</id>
    <published>2017-03-26T23:00:03Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-27T06:00:22Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/3e688fbc491d6d2db77b4035c5ad5b2c"/>
    <title>Human oral microbiome crisis at the end of 18th c.?</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.438198</doi>
    <content type="html">Scholars have recently shown a clear increase in the frequency of caries and tooth loss for humans after the end of the 18th c. [1] For the authors, changes in nutrition (more sugar) and dental health (possibly higher frequency of tooth extraction) could be the underlying factors which led to this minor to moderate shift of dental disease frequencies in Europe. In fact, other major factors may have play a key-role at this period [2], causing a modification of oral microbiome, especially at the level of the dental plaque: introduction of first vaccinations (smallpox), apparition and/or increase of the consummation of new aliments (potatoes, coffee, chocolate, tomatoes, maize, etc.) or drugs (tobacco), beginning of the industrial revolution (with subsequent changes in the time and mode of work, and the adaptation of human biology to it). Further metagenomic analysis of dental calculus will be necessary to investigate any significant modification of the oral microbiome that could confirm or not this hypothesis, comparable to the procedures used for the evolutionary stages of pre-humans, but on a wider scale.

References
1. Müller A, Hussein K. Meta-analysis of teeth from European populations before and after the 18th century reveals a shift towards increased prevalence of caries and tooth loss. Arch Oral Biol. 2017;73:7-15.
2. Andrews K. History of medicine: Health, medicine and disease in the eighteenth century. Br J 18th Cent Stud. 2011; 34: 503-15.</content>
    <author>
      <name>Charlier, Philippe</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/773</id>
    <published>2020-07-21T03:24:19Z</published>
    <updated>2020-07-21T06:01:44Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/9fe380f137306382cc7e2798f6960c26"/>
    <title>Explanation for spheno-ethmoid contact on the organ-crowded hominoid anterior cranial floor</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3953298</doi>
    <content type="html">The anterior cranial floor is variably configured in primates. The [sphenoid and ethmoid bones contact each other](https://www.worldcat.org/title/mans-place-among-the-mammals/oclc/1463021) in strepsirrhines, orangutans, and modern humans, whereas a [horizontal plate of frontal bone](https://www.jstor.org/stable/3031137?seq=1) interrupts spheno-ethmoid contact in Old World monkeys, lesser apes, and, more variably, in New World monkeys and African great apes. Frontal contribution to the midline anterior cranial floor has been tied to [differential growth of the brain and orbits](https://www.worldcat.org/title/mans-place-among-the-mammals/oclc/1463021), [developmental competition for space](https://books.google.com/books/about/Trait%C3%A9_d_anatomie_humaine_Nouvelle_%C3%A9di.html?id=GiLocQAACAAJ), [upper facial prognathism](https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/ajpa.1330010208), and [size of the supraorbital ridges](https://openlibrary.org/books/OL6093349M/Evolution_emerging). In anthropoids, the jugum sphenoidale and cribriform plate scale isometrically with brain size but total anterior cranial floor length scales with negative allometry, leaving [insufficient room for frontal contribution to the midline at larger brain sizes](https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0047248400904469). These allometric “spatial packing” limitations may explain secondarily-derived spheno-ethmoid contact in large-brained African apes, but the underlying scaling relationships need to be tested intraspecifically. Spheno-ethmoid contact in orangutans, on the other hand, may be the byproduct of crowding a [large](https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0047248401905378?via%3Dihub), [projecting](https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0047248410002034?via%3Dihub) temporal lobe and [dorsally-rotated cribriform plate](https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/ajpa.1330010208) onto the endocranial surface. These ideas are consistent with the hypothesis that spheno-ethmoid contact at the level of the anterior cranial floor is not developmentally homologous in small- and large- brained primates.</content>
    <author>
      <name>McCarthy, Robert</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
