<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:/collections/fc844a3d6d5d548e8e7f34d12aed0802</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/collections/fc844a3d6d5d548e8e7f34d12aed0802.atom"/>
  <title>Journal of Brief Ideas: Collection test my own</title>
  <updated>2022-11-04T06:32:10Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/1012</id>
    <published>2022-10-05T14:56:15Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-07T02:37:57Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/219d1ff87d596119734038cfa140f4b0"/>
    <title>Using Fig in China to Explore New Criteria to Grade Edible Landscape Plants </title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7232626</doi>
    <content type="html">Conventional wisdom accepts that selecting a fruit tree for landscape involves very different priorities than for commercial farming, e.g. extended season instead of concentrated, lower sugar concentration in fruit instead of higher. However, landscaping practices can cause plant to vary so significantly from its farm counterparts of the same exact variety in terms of hardiness, fertility, crop, vigor and yield that almost render its morphological information invalid. 

Fig (Ficus carica L.) is a fruiting shrub widely used in landscape. While reputable nurseries have graded “Qingpi” fig to be a cold-hardy, easy-bearing, biferous, vigorous and bountiful variety in a given region of China, landscape architects reported disappointment. Random controlled trials disclosed that the unique pruning practice in landscape is relevant and causational; past studies on the genetics of amino acid uptake for fruit flavor hinted a different composting strategy for better shape formation. Nurseries may consider adding criteria “hardiness when heavily pruned” “fertility when heavily pruned” etc. when grading fig seedlings for sale.

This could be a groundwork for future research of and with traditional nurseries, for eventually constructing a new grading system for a new market, and for fruit trees becoming viable, sustainable and aesthetically-manageable for landscape architects. </content>
    <author>
      <name>Wu, Di</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:beta.briefideas.org,2005:Idea/901</id>
    <published>2021-12-31T03:45:41Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-07T02:38:21Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/5bf081466bfc36efe4ede2acf7e208b3"/>
    <title>Human Enhanced AI Translation Should Pioneer in Aiding Underdeveloped Areas to Fight Pandemics</title>
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5816283</doi>
    <content type="html">COVID outbreaks have highlighted the importance of collaboration across geographical and political borders. Yet the English terminology associated with it can be confusing when multiple English-as-Second-or-Other-Language (ESOL) jurisdictions are involved, especially when they each have used and developed unique abbreviations.  Artificial Intelligence (AI) translation alone won't help as it is based on one standard fused from multiple inputs, while such communication requires understanding of multiple standards. Several trials proved one practice helpful: prior to a meeting, each ESOL party provides a translator to convert their respective native languages to an machine-ready extent, clearing ambiguities and misunderstandings, and then leave the meeting to the hands of AI translation, with human translators interfering when necessary. </content>
    <author>
      <name>Wu, Di</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
